Richard Donohue | curriculum vitae

Department of Geography, University of Kentucky 805-A Patterson Office Tower • rgdonohue@uky.edu

RESEARCH and EXPERIENCE

My training and scholarship bridges the technical implementation of emerging geospatial technologies with GIScience and Web Cartography research. In particular, my work is focused upon web map interface design in support of cartographic interaction and Geovisualization. I specialize in the identification of new geospatial technologies and application of professional cartographic workflows for improved map product research, development, and location based services.

CURRENT APPOINTMENTS

2014 – PRESENT **Postdoctoral Researcher,** Web Cartography

Department of Geography, University of Kentucky

EDUCATION

2014 **Doctor of Philosophy** in Geography, Minor in Science and Technology

Studies, The University of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, WI.

Dissertation: "Web Mapping with Web Standards: Teaching, Learning, and

Using Open Source Web Mapping Technologies"

Dissertation Chair: Robert Roth

2004 **Master of Arts** in Education, *The University of Colorado at Boulder,*

Boulder, CO.

2000 **Bachelor of Arts** in Philosophy and Political Science (double major), Fort

Lewis College, Durango, CO.

PUBLICATIONS

2016 (forthcoming) Zook M, A Poortuis, and **RG Donohue**. "Mapping Spaces: Cartographic

Representations of Online Data," in Handbook of Online Research

Methods, second edition.

2015 Sack CM, **RG Donohue**, and RE Roth. "Multivariate Choropleth Maps with

D3," Cartographic Perspectives, 76.

2014 Roth, RE, **RG Donohue**, CM Sack, TR Wallace, and TMA Buckingham.

"Evaluating Evolving Web Mapping Technologies." Cartographic

Perspectives.

2014 **Donohue RG**, CM Sack, and RE Roth. "Time Series Proportional Symbol

Maps with Leaflet and JQuery." Cartographic Perspectives, 75.

2014	Janicki J, G Guo, M Conway, RG Donohue , and RE Roth. "Weevil Viewer: An interactive mapping application for geographic and phenological exploration of Wisconsin's primitive weevils." <i>The Journal of Maps</i> , 10(2): 289–296.
2013	Donohue RG , CM Sack, TR Wallace, RE Roth, and TMA Buckingham. "A competitive analysis of open web mapping technologies." In: <i>Proceedings of the 26th International Cartographic Conference</i> . Dresden, Germany: August 27.
2013	Roth RE, RG Donohue , CM Sack, TR Wallace, and TMA Buckingham. "A process for assessing emergent web mapping technologies." In: <i>Proceedings of the 26th International Cartographic Conference</i> . Dresden, Germany: August 26.
2010	Donohue RG . "Denis Wood." In: Barney Warf (ed) <i>The Encyclopedia of Geography</i> . Thousand Oaks, CA: SAGE Publications, pp. 3122-3123.
2007	Harrower M, RG Donohue . "An Interactive Cultural Map of Wisconsin." <i>Proceedings of the 32nd Annual SSHA Conference</i> , Chicago, IL. November 15–18.
2006	Wolgemuth J, RG Donohue . "Toward an inquiry of discomfort guiding transformation in "emancipatory" narrative research." Qualitative <i>Inquiry</i> , 12(5): 1012-1021.
2006	Crane R, L Pedersen–Gallegos, S Laursen, E Seymour, and Donohue, RG . "Schema disjunction among undergraduate women in computer science." <i>Encyclopedia of Gender and Information Technology</i> , ed. E. M. Trauth. Hershey, PA, London: Idea Group Reference, pp. 1087–1091.

CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS	
2015	Donohue RG (presenter) and M Zook. "The OpenSource Web Mapping Workflow: QGIS, Leaflet and UI/UX." <i>Kentucky Association of Mapping Professionals 2015 GIS Conference</i> . Owensboro, KY: October 13.
2015	Aileen B, A Robinson, J Kerski, P Drews, RG Donohue (panel discussant), "Geography and Online Education B: What is the status of online geography and geospatial education and its impact on traditional educational offerings?" <i>2015 Annual Meeting of the Association of American Geographers</i> . Chicago, IL: April 22.
2014	Crampton J, RG Donohue (panel discussant), L Mogel, A Robinson, RE Roth, MW Wilson, and M Zook. "Adventures in Online Mapping Education in the 21st Century." <i>North American Cartographic and Information Society (NACIS) Annual Meeting</i> . Pittsburg, PA: October 9.
2014	Czaplewski J (presenter), RG Donohue , and R Mead. "Responsive Interactivity: Toward User-centered Adaptive Map Experiences." <i>Free and Open Source Software for Geospatial (FOSS4G) North America</i> . Portland OR: September 11.
2013	Donohue RG (presenter), A Poorthuis, and Z Johnson. "Bill Bunge, D3.js, and the Future of Critical Cartography." <i>North American Cartographic and Information Society (NACIS) Annual Meeting</i> . Greenville, SC: October 11.

2013	Sack CS (presenter), RG Donohue , RE Roth, TR Wallace, and TMA Buckingham. "Adapting web mapping curriculum to open source technologies." <i>Free and Open Source Software for Geospatial (FOSS4G) North America</i> . Minneapolis, MN: May 22.
2013	Roth RE, CS Sack (co-presenter), RG Donohue (co-presenter), TR Wallace, and TMA Buckingham. "Web mapping technology study update, or what you just learned now is obsolete." UW–Madison Geospatial Alliance Summit. Madison, WI: April 25.
2013	Roth RE (presenter), RG Donohue , TR Wallace, CS Sack, and TMA Buckingham. "Getting a handle on open source web mapping technologies." <i>Wisconsin Land Information Association (WLIA) 2013 Annual Conference</i> . Lake Geneva, WI: February 14.
2012	Donohue RG , T Wallace, CS Sack, RE Roth, and TMA Buckingham "Keeping Pace with Emerging Web Mapping Technologies." <i>North American Cartographic and Information Society (NACIS) Annual Meeting</i> . Portland, OR: October 19.
2012	Donohue RG . "Renewable Energy Landscapes and the Circulation of Technoscience through Wind Farm Development and Debates." 2012 Annual Meeting of the Association of American Geographers. New York, NY: February 24.
2010	Donohue RG (panel discussant). "Geography, Technology and Science." 17th Annual Critical Geography Mini–Conference. Milwaukee, WI: November 6.
2008	Donohue RG. "Emerging Technologies in Mapping: Public Participation and Distributed Mapping." <i>Holtz Center for Science and Technology Studies Brown Bag Series</i> , UW–Madison, WI.
2008	Donohue RG. "Digital Mapping Technologies: Implications for Knowledge Spaces." 2008 Meeting of the Association of American Geographers. Boston, MA.

OTHER PRESENTATIONS (INTERNAL)

2015	Donohue RG. Geo309: Introduction to GIS. "The QGIS to Leaflet Web Mapping Workflow" (guest lecture). Lexington, KY: November 6.
2015	Donohue RG. Geo222: Cities of the World. "The Ephemeral and Utopian Experiment: Black Rock City" (guest lecture). Lexington, KY: November 3.
2015	Donohue RG. "The Power of Abstraction: Principles of Cartography" (guest lecture). <i>Geo109: Digital Mapping</i> . Lexington, KY: October 6.

TEACHING

Instructor of Record, Department of Geography, UW-Madison

2011, Spring Lecturer, Geog378: Introduction to Geocomputing

Teaching Assistant, Department of Geography, UW-Madison

2013, Spring	Lab Instructor, Geog575: Interactive Cartography & Geovisualization
2012, Fall	Lab Instructor, Geog 572: Graphic Design in Cartography
2012, Spring	Lab Instructor, Geog575: Interactive Cartography & Geovisualization
2011, Fall	Teaching Assistant, Geog565: Undergraduate Research Colloquium
2010, Spring	Lab Instructor, Geog676: Geocomputing

PAST EMPLOYMENT

2013 – 2014	Project Assistant and Website Developer/Content Manager, College of Agriculture and Life Sciences (CALS), Research Division
2013 (summer)	Consultant, Department of Geography, University of Kentucky, Cartographic Curriculum Camp. May 27 – June 4
2010	Project Assistant for GIS Certificate Program, Department of Geography, UW-Madison
2007 – 2010	Webmaster, Department of Geography, UW–Madison
2006 – 2009	Project Assistant and Program Evaluator for the Wisconsin Alliance for Minority Participation (WiscAMP), <i>The University of Wisconsin-Madison</i>
2004 – 2006	Professional Research Assistant, Ethnography & Evaluation Research (E&ER), <i>The University of Colorado at Boulder</i>

AWARDS and HONORS

2015	Undergraduate Exceptional Pedagogy Award, Department of Geography, University of Kentucky
2014	Trewartha Travel Award, Department of Geography, UW–Madison
2013	College of Letters and Science TA Exceptional Service award (nominated, Department of Geography, UW-Madison)
2013	Trewartha Travel Award, Department of Geography, UW–Madison
2012	College of Letters and Science TA Exceptional Service award (nominated, Department of Geography, UW-Madison)
2012	Trewartha Travel Award, Department of Geography, UW–Madison
2010	Holtz Center for Science and Technology Studies 2010 Graduate Scholars Summer Fellowship, UW-Madison
2008	Trewartha Travel Award, Department of Geography, UW–Madison
2007	Holtz Center for Science and Technology Studies 2007 Graduate Scholars Summer Fellowship, UW-Madison

CURRENT AFFILIATIONS

North American Cartographic Information Society (NACIS) The New Mappings Collaboratory, University of Kentucky

SERVICE

2012–2013	Speakers Committee, Graduate Student Representative, Department of Geography, UW–Madison
2008 – 2010	Madison Area Cartographic Design and Debate (MACDAD) Committee Coordinator, Department of Geography, UW-Madison